Furth, Otto; Papers ger037
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Otto Furth Papers
1912-1986
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger037
4 cubic ft.
This collection predominantly contains German and English manuscripts, plays, poetry, lectures, and articles in newspapers and magazines, 1933-1969. There is also correspondence with friends, writers and with Twentieth Century Fox pertaining to copyright infringement, 1940-1948. Otto Furth also wrote under the pseudonym Owen Elford.
Collection X
Biographical / Historical
Otto Fürth was born in Strakonitz, Bohemia, Germany, on November 7, 1894 where he spent the first four years of his childhood. In 1899 his father, Hugo Fürth, relocated the family to Vienna, Austria where he opened a fez factory, the Aktiengesellschaft der Oesterreichischen Fezfabriken.
Otto Fürth spent the next fifteen years of his life in Vienna, where he attended school and then university to study law, philosophy and literature. His university studies were interrupted by the onset of World War I and Fürth's enlistment in the army early in 1915. He was soon shipped to the Russian front, where he was eventually promoted to lieutenant of the artillery division. On July 4, 1916 he was captured and sent to Siberia, where he spent the next three and a half years. Fürth finally managed to escape with a friend and spent the next six years teaching French and German at a German school in Tientsin, China, until he was able to secure passage on a Danish ship headed for Copenhagen.
In 1920 Fürth finally returned to Vienna, where he finished his university degree during the next two years and took a position in the family factory. Fürth spent the next years in Vienna, married Gertrude Harteck in 1924, had daughter Irmgard (1926) and son Harald (1930), and continued to advance in his career. At the same time, he continued to write, a career he always considered secondary. Nonetheless, early in 1931 saw the first performance of his play "Der Mann ohne Privatleben" in the Deutsches Volkstheater, Vienna. Although this play achieved moderate success, traveled to a number of European theaters, and had the film rights purchased by Paramount, the most successful of Fürth's plays was the comedy "Zehn Gesichter gegen eins."
With the takeover of Austria by Hitler in 1938, Fürth immediately applied for visas to the United States for himself and his family. Not wishing to wait any longer in Vienna, in August 1939, Fürth took his family to Switzerland, where they stayed for the next year and a half. Finally on August 28, 1941, Fürth and his family arrived in New York harbor.
Fürth, with the aid of a relative, soon secured a position as an accountant for the Wall Street firm of Lazard Frères, a position which he held until his retirement in 1964. Fürth continued to write after his arrival in the United States. His one successful full-length novel, Men in Black (published in 1942 under the pseudonym Owen Elford), was first written in German and translated by Richard Winston into English.
Although Otto Fürth considered himself first and foremost a businessman, and a writer only as a pastime, his literary production consisted of numerous plays (mostly comedies), countless poems, newspaper articles, movie script ideas and one full-length published novel. Fürth died in New York on December 15, 1979.
Scope and Contents
Although this collection contains some biographical materials, documents and correspondence, the bulk consists of Fürth's writings, both in published and in manuscript form. There are examples of Fürth's writings from all genres, including poetry, drama, television and film, prose and essayistic writings, and his literary output spans over six decades.
Although there is very little correspondence in the collection, Fürth's legal battles against RKO studios over his claim to the screenplay rights for the film Tom, Dick and Harry (1941), are well documented.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In 1981, Harold P. Furth, son of Otto Furth donated this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Fürth, Otto, 1894-1979; Manuscripts for publication; Screenplays; Correspondence
- Biographical Materials, 1939-1978; 8 folders
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes several short biographical statements prepared by Fürth, clippings about him, as well as some documents relating to Fürth, his wife, and several family members.
  - Autobiographical statements, short introductions, 1942-1975; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autobiographical statement."Siberien 1916-1920", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical information and clippings about Fürth, 1956-1978; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Documents, including passports, photo, 1939-1941; 1943; 1989; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fürth, Hans. Documents, biographical statement, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fürth, Margarethe / Gertrude Fleischmann / Anny Steinbrener. Documents, 1939-1940; Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fürth, Rosalie. "Aus meinen Strakonitzer Erinnerungen." Autobiographical statement, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lehman, Edith Altschul (cousin of Otto Fürth, wife of Herbert Lehman). Family tree, 1976-1977; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1919-1986; 23 folders
  This series contains isolated letters over the years, including some with relatives. One folder of special interest contains letters received by Fürth relating to his time in Tientsin, China, 1919-1921.
  The majority of this series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence during Fürth's period in Tientsin, 1919-1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Aktiengesellschaft der Österreichischen Fezfabriken, 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Altschul, Frank (cousin), 1942-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Atteslander, Pierre E. (Robert Durrer Case), 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Austrian Institute (Richard Sickinger), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bender, Wilhelm, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brüll, Leo, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Burghauser, Hugo, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Contract
  - Fleischmann, Inge Steer, 1976; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fürth, Gertrude (Trudl – wife), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fürth, Richard (cousin), 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gmeiner, Hermann, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Häussermann, Ernst, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Harteck, Paul (brother-in-law), 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Holt, Hans, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jantsch, Karl, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Keller, Rudolf (Schweizer Feuilleton-Dienst), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Knüsel, Jakob, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - König, Steffi, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Lederer, Hans, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Documents
  - Lehman, Herbert H, 1942-1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Neugebauer, Alfred, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Niers, Gert, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ostheim, Fritz, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Pelikan, Maria, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Reisser, H., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Rusch, Franz, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Spalek, John M. (re: Otto Fürth Papers), 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Steinbrener, Hans Th., 1946-1971 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Taussig, Gustav, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Zdansky, Erich, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Zemen, Josef, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous and Unidentified, Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Fürth vs. RKO, 1940-1948; 11 folders
  This series is related to the plagerism case surrounding Fürth's play, Dorothea mit Variationen. It contains correspondence, legal documents, as well as both Fürth's version and Paul Jarrico's version of the screen plays, which were the basis of the film Tom, Dick and Harry, starring Ginger Rogers.
  - Correspondence, Dorothea mit Variationen, (including: Gustave L. Goldstein, Paul Koretz, Ernst Wolfgang Korngold, Alvin Kronacher, George Marton, Emil Oprecht, David Regosin), 1940-1948 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, Dorothea mit Variationen, (including: transcripts and translations of important letters), 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence file from Fürth's lawyer's, 1944-1947 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Documents re: Fürth vs. RKO, including depositions, 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Dorothea mit Variationen, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Film script. 2 copies
  - Dorothea mit Variationen, Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Typescript. 42p.
  - Dorothea mit Variationen, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Typescript. 41p.
  - Dorothea mit Variationen vs. Tom, Dick and Harry. Discussions of the similarities between the two pieces, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Fürth vs. RKO. Clippings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Jarrico, Paul. "Star Light, Star Bright", Undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Typescript of film script. 2 copies, 19p. ea.
  - Miscellaneous notes, stenographer's notes re: Fürth vs. RKO, Undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Writings of Otto Fürth, 1912-1979; 166 folders
  This series represents the bulk of the collection and contains typescripts and handwritten manuscripts written by Fürth over a sixty year period. The series contains poetry (8 file folders), plays (37 file folders), film and TV sketches (17 file folders), prose writings (22 file folders), essayistic writings (82 file folders) and published reviews of Fürth's writings (4 file folders). Included in the prose writings are several versions of the unpublished autobiographical Flucht aus dem Schicksal, as well as the original translation by Richard Winston of Fürth's novel Men in Black (published under the pseudonym Owen Elford).
  Arranged by format, then alphabetically.
  - Poem: "Begegnungen. Versuch einer Selbstbiographie in Versen.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    2 copies, photocopies, 38p. ea.
  - Poem: "Begegnungen mit anderen und mit mir.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Photocopy of typescript.
  - Typescripts of individual poems, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Early poems, bound volume, Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Early handwritten poems (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Poems, 1912-1974 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Typed and handwritten.
  - Poems, marked "Alte und neue Gedichte und Duplikate.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Primarily typescript.
  - Poems, marked "Duplikaten von Gedichten.", Undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Typescript.
  - PlayScripts: "Eine Affentragödie in 4 Akten.", 1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Playscript. 2 copies, one with the handwritten comment "Copyright by Otto Fürth 1925."
  - PlayScripts: "Eine Affentragödie in 4 Aufzügen.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Original typescript, with comment "Alte Fassung." 57p.
  - PlayScripts: "Eine Affentragödie" in vier Akten, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Photocopy of typescript with the comment "Alte, überholte Wiener Fassung." 49p.
  - PlayScripts: "Eine Affentragödie in vier Akten, mit einem Prolog und Epilog.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Original typescript and two additional photocopies. Version (ca. 1936) used for a reading in 1975. 47p.
  - PlayScripts: "Fountain of Youth." English version of "Eine Affentragödie.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Original typescript and one photocopied version, with the comment "Harolds Übersetzung der ursprünglichen Fassung." Undated. 67p.
  - PlayScripts: "Barbara and the Bonus.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    2 copies. Original typescript; one photocopy. 22p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Faust in Riverdale.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Typescript (carbon). 3p.
  - PlayScripts: "Gift! Komödie in drei Akten (4 Bildern).", Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    List of characters, synopses of acts. Typescript (carbon). 12p.
  - PlayScripts: "Kurzschluß.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Bound carbon copy typescript with corr., under the original title "Kuss im Dunkel." Acts numbered individually.
  - PlayScripts: "Kurzschluß.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Bound copy with original title "Kuss im Dunkeln" scratched out and new title written in by hand, "Kurzschluss (Komödie eines Kusses)." Another identical copy with revised cover page.
  - PlayScripts: "Kurzschluss (Die Komoedie eines Kusses). Lustspiel in 3 Aufzügen.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Bound carbon copy typescript, pages numbered consecutively. 64p.
  - PlayScripts: "Kurzschluss.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Typescripts. 3 copies, one original typescript, one carbon, one photocopy. 50p. 13. "Der Mann ohne Privatleben. Komödie in drei Akten (vier Bildern)." Playscript. 2 copies (No. 15, No. 45), one containing errata sheets. Copyright 1931, Verlag Max Pfeffer, Wien-Berlin.
  - PlayScripts: "Der Mann ohne Privatleben. Komödie in drei Akten (vier Bildern).", Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Playscript. 2 copies (No. 15, No. 45), one containing errata sheets. Copyright 1931, Verlag Max Pfeffer, Wien-Berlin.
  - PlayScripts: "L'uomo senza vita privata." Italian translation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Typescript (carbon) with corr. 66p.
  - PlayScripts: "The man who had no private life.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    2 copies. Original typescript, with the note "Haralds Übersetzung." Another carbon copy. 80p. ea. Additional suggestions for a movie version of the play. T. 3p.
  - PlayScripts: "Marc Aurel. Schauspiel in vier Aufzügen.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Typescript (carbon). 95p.
  - PlayScripts: "Marc Aurel. Schauspiel in 5 Akten (16 Bildern).", Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Typescript (carbon). 99p.
  - PlayScripts: "Marc Aurel. Schauspiel in 5 Akten von Johannes Gorner.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Listed under a pseudonym. Typescript (carbon). 105p.
  - PlayScripts: "Marc Aurel. Schauspiel in fünf Akten.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    3 copies, one bound typescript, two photocopies. 111p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Marc Aurel. Schauspiel in 5 Akten.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    2 copies, one bound original typescript, one bound carbon. 111p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Marc Aurel." Synopsis, list of characters, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Photocopy. 6p
  - PlayScripts: "Marc Aurel. Schauspiel in fünf Akten.", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Photocopy of published version, 1969.
  - PlayScripts: "Zwei Dutzend rote Rosen. Lustspiel in 3 Akten (5 Bildern) von Otto Fürth unter Zugrundelegung der gleichnamigen Komödie des Aldo de Benedetti." Early version of "Der Spielverderber.", ca. 1934 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Typescript. 117p.
  - PlayScripts: "Zwei Dutzend rote Rosen. Lustspiel in 3 Akten (5 Bildern) von Otto Fürth unter Zugrundelegung der gleichnamigen Komödie des Aldo de Benedetti." Early version of "Der Spielverderber.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    2 copies, typescript (carbon). 117p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Der Spielverderber. Komödie in drei Akten." Revised version of "Zwei Dutzend rote Rosen" with names of characters changed from original, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    2 copies, typescript (carbon). 99p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Der Spielverderber. Komödie in drei Akten.", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    3 copies, typescript (carbon). 81p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Der Spielverderber. (Synopsis der Komödie.)", Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Typescripts. 2 versions. 24p., 6p.
  - PlayScripts: "Der Spielverderber." Synopsis, with the note "Entwurf für Robert Stolz.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    2 copies, 1p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Was wissen Sie von Ihrer Frau? Gesellschaftskomödie in 6 Bildern., Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    2 copies. Typescript (carbon), 67p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Was wissen Sie von Ihrer Frau? Gesellschaftskomödie in 6 Bilder.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    2 copies, one bound, one photocopy. Copyright 1933 by Verlag Max Pfeffer, Wien-Berlin. 69p. ea.
  - PlayScripts: "Was wissen Sie von Ihrer Frau? Gesellschaftskomödie in sechs Bildern.", Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Typescript (carbon). Copyright Washington D.C. 1933 by Verlag Max Pfeffer, Berlin-Wien. 74p.
  - PlayScripts: "Flirt mit dem Unbekannten. Gesellschaftskomödie in 6 Bildern." Alternative title for "Was wissen Sie von Ihrer Frau?", Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Typescript (carbon). 88p.
  - PlayScripts: "Zehn Gesichter gegen eins. Komödie zwischen Zweien." Playscript, with the comment "ursprüngliche Fassung." Max Reichard-Verlag, Freiburg im Breisgau, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    83p.
  - PlayScripts: "Zehn Gesichter gegen eins. Komödie zwischen Zweien." Playscript. Verlag Max Pfeffer, New York, Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    77p.
  - Playscripts: "Zehn Gesichter gegen eins. Komödie zwischen Zweien." ( 1 of 2), Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    5 copies, original typescript, carbon typescript, 3 photocopies. 60p. ea.
  - Playscripts: "Zehn Gesichter gegen eins. Komödie zwischen Zweien." (2 of 2), Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Playscripts: "Zehn Gesichter gegen eins." Prose version, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Typescript. 20p. Also 2p. "Worte an den Zuschauer." Film sketches, TV script sketches, play sketches
  - Playscripts: "The Airraid Warden.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Typescript. 10p.
  - Playscripts: "The Dragoman.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Typescript. 4p.
  - Playscripts: "Flucht nach oben.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Typescript (carbon). 21p.
  - Playscripts: "Freedom of Speech – or safety first?", Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Typescript. 3p.
  - Playscripts: "Get Yourself a Girl.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Typescript. 2p.
  - Playscripts: "Hochverrat.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Typescript. 30p.
  - Playscripts: "Treason." English version of "Hochverrat.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 13p. ea.
  - Playscripts: "Hoppen und Malz … gewonnen!", Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Typescript (carbon). 19p.
  - Playscripts: "… in die weite Welt hinein… Ballett-Entwurf.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Typescript (carbon). 17p.
  - Playscripts: "Der Millionaer und der Flickschuster.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 8p. ea.
  - Playscripts: "The Millionaire and the Cobbler.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    English translation 2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 8p. ea.
  - Playscripts: "Not Exactly…", Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 17p. ea.
  - Playscripts: "Peabody versus Peabody.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 2p. ea. German version. 1p.
  - Playscripts: "Puppies.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 6p. ea.
  - Playscripts: "Verdunkelung.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Typescript (carbon). 6p.
  - Playscripts: "Vorarbeiten für Mond-Sketch." Handwritten notes in spiral notebook., Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Playscripts: Untitled sketches, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Typescripts.
  - Prose Writings: "An Easy Escape from Siberia.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 29p. ea. Introductory statement. 1p
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." (1 of 2), Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Typescript (carbon). 304p.
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." (2 of 2), Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Part 1: "Aufbruch.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 62p. ea
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Part 2: "Eine leichte Flucht aus Siberien.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. Pp. 63-113.
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Part 3: "Buergerliches Zwischenspiel.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. Pp. 114-168.
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Part 4: "Der zweite Aufbruch.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. Pp. 169-310.
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Part 5: "Das Atlantische Jenseits.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. Pp. 311-361.
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Extra pages, Undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Typescript (carbon).
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Prose Writings: "Flucht aus dem Schicksal." Deleted pages, Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Prose Writings: "Kampf mit Sybill.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 52p. ea. Handwritten version in two notebooks.
  - Prose Writings: "Der Einsiedler von Tientsin" (changed to: "Der letzte Schritt des Dr. Murck")., 1920 November (Box 3, Folder 33)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon, dated Nov. 1920. 23p. ea. Another version. Typescript. 30p.
  - Prose Writings: "Der letzte Schritt des Dr. Murck.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Typescript (carbon). 30p. Excerpt for reading at the Austrian Institute. Typescript.
  - Prose Writings: "Der letzte Schritt des Dr. Murck.", Undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    2 copies. Typescript, carbon. 19p. ea.
  - Prose Writings: "Men in Black." English translation by Richard Winston., Undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    Typescript. With numberous corr. 212p.
  - Prose Writings: "Die schwarze Geige." (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Typescript. 20p.
  - Prose Writings: "The Black Violin/Fiddle" (English version of "Die schwarze Geige"). Various drafts, versions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Prose Writings:. Reviews of books by Otto Fürth, prepared for discussions at the Criticism Club., Undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Prose Writings: "Goethe." Typescript of lecture, 1979 May (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Prose Writings: "Kuesse in Amerika." Typescript of lecture, 1975 April (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Prose Writings: Fragments. Typed and handwritten, Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - The Man Who Had No Private Life. Clippings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Marc Aurel. Clippings., Undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Men in Black. Clippings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Die schwarze Geige. Clippings., Undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Essayistic writings: "The American Way of Life.", 1967 September (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Typescript (Carbon), 4p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Amerikanische Aristokraten.", 1963 May (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Typescript (Carbon, 3p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Die amerikanische Rundschau. 'Religion und das Gute Leben.' Horace L. Friess.", Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Typescript (carbon), 19p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Die amerikanische Kronprinzen.", 1972 August (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Typescript (carbon), 3p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Amerikas entrechtete Majoritaet.", 1970 January (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Typescript (carbon), 4p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Arbeiterbewegung ohne Arbeiterpartei. (Die Gewerkschaften in Amerika).", 1969 November (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Typescript (carbon), 9p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Birken in Amerika.", Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Typescript (carbon), n.d. 4p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Brillen auf allen Nasen.", 1969 January (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Essayistic writings: "Broadway-Streiflicht.", Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Typescript (carbon), n.d. 5p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Commuter in New York.", 1962 October (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Essayistic writings: "Dachstubenromantik in Amerika.", Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Typescript (carbon), n.d. 6p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Donner und Demokratie (Prozess gegen Wolkenraub).", Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    2 copies, typescript and carbon, n.d. (1950). 3p. ea.
  - Essayistic writings: "Ein Galsritter reitet durch das Establishment.", 1971 May (Box 4, Folder 13)
    3 copies, carbon typescript and photocopies, 4p. ea.
  - Essayistic writings: "Ein Haus fuer Weltbuerger.", Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Essayistic writings: "Ein Luxushotel im Weltenraum.", 1973 April (Box 4, Folder 15)
    2 copies, typescript and carbon, 2p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Ein Plaidoyer gegen Sterilisation.", Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Typescript (carbon), 11p.
  - Essayistic writings: "Ein witziger Praesident?", Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Typescript (carbon), (1952). 2p.